again every time you go through the
sanctuary and
its services you're learning two things
very two very important things
one you're learning all of the different
movements of
christ that he made that he might be one
with us that he may save us
two you're learning also how we respond
to the sacrifice of christ and the work
of jesus and what he's doing to save us
and i'll give you a great example of
that you just heard how the courtyard
it talks about how uh the lamb would be
laid on the altar and would die
for our sins but then uh as you heard
reference earlier she quoted romans 6
but when you go to romans 6 and verse 12
or verse 11 and 12
it talks about how we are to be dead
indeed unto sin
you know romans 12 tells us that we are
to present our bodies
as a living sacrifice and so we can
watch some parallels
between the work that christ did for our
salvation
and the work we are to do in response to
that salvation so when you study the
sanctuary the the best way to understand
the sanctuary
is to understand those two key points
seeing
what christ has done and is doing for us
and then how we are to respond
to what christ has done and is doing for
us
anybody who approaches the sanctuary in
that way you will behold
wondrous things out of the law of god
you're going to see amazing things
from scripture so let me go ahead and
share my screen just for a moment
and uh i'm going to draw us too hold on
i got to pull that up
and yeah there we are okay
so when we look at this here i'm just
going to go ahead and uh
point us to this you know one of the
things i like to do is i like to
kind of summarize the work of jesus in
the sanctuary
and the things that lead up to it i see
the courtyard
not so much as the sanctuary but i see
the courtyard leading to
the sanctuary and when we think about
that watch this
the courtyard we know is you know that's
the exact word that's used
in ezekiel 10 and verse 5. there's a
courtyard
and then after the court in the
courtyard jesus is the lamb that dies
for us
i just want to keep it super simple in
the courtyard
jesus is the lamb that dies for us in
the holy place
you'll find the holy place specifically
written reference
as a matter of fact you'll find the term
holy place
and most holy place you'll find both of
those referenced in exodus 26 and verse
33.
it is in the holy place that jesus
is the priest that lives and intercedes
for us
so again in the courtyard jesus is the
lamb
that dies for us in the holy place he is
our priest
that lives and intercedes for us in the
most holy place
he's our high priest advocate and judge
and so when i when i think about this
whole service or these these structures
courtyard
holy place most holy place i put forth a
summary in my mind
that summary is in courtyard he's the
lamb that dies for us
holy place he's the priest that lives
and intercedes for us
most holy place he's my high priest that
is my advocate and my
judge and then i begin to just watch
how this unfolds all throughout
scripture now when we think about the
holy place there are basically three
articles of furniture
you have the table of shoe bread you
have the seven lamps
some called the golden candle sticks and
then you have that altar
of incense and in all three of these we
see things again
that we can learn about jesus but then
we can also see a response
that we can give to him so an example is
is in john chapter
six uh jesus refers to himself when you
think of the table of shoe bread
jesus also refers to himself as the
bread of life we see this in john
chapter six and uh let's see
john chapter six yeah in john chapter
six we can look at verse
you know 54 who so eateth my flesh
and drinketh my blood hath eternal life
and i will raise him up at the last day
for my flesh is meat indeed my blood is
drink indeed he that eateth my flesh and
drinketh my blood dwelleth in me and i
in him
as a living father hath sent me and i
live by the father so he that eateth me
even he shall live
by me this is that bread which came down
from heaven
not as your fathers did eat manna and
are dead he that eateth of this bread
shall live forever
jesus would use himself as an anti-type
of bread when it was used in these
symbolic ways whether it was the
manna coming down from heaven or if it's
the bread that's being used
in the sanctuary jesus is that bread
of life then of course we have the
golden candlesticks
christ is the light of the world john 9
and verse 5 as long as i am in the world
i am the light of the world one of the
things that i think is really
significant too
is that the lights in the candlesticks
in the holy place
were never to go out it was never
supposed to go out it always stays
lit and i think that that's a beautiful
thing to know that when christ desires
to come in your heart he's not trying to
make a part-time residence
he wants to have a full-time residence
in your heart he always wants his light
to shine we should never
as children of god reward ourselves for
doing good for a period of time
and start saying now that i've done good
for so long let me start dimming the
light
and turning down my light no the bible
says let your light go shine
that you know men may see your good
works and glorify your father in heaven
christ does not want part-time residents
in you he wants full-time residents in
you
he wants the light to always shine
through you
not just when you're at work not just
when you're at church
not just when you're around your people
god says even when you're home
even when you're by yourself and you
have high speed internet in your hand
and you have any website that you can go
through god says remember the light
remember that you're a child of light
remember the light is to always
shine and so you you get practical
lessons
when you study the sanctuary i mean it's
just beautiful
god is that light the incense is very
powerful
because the incense can represent two
things
one the incense was something that was a
very sweet smell it had a very beautiful
smell
and uh it was very pleasing to god when
you look at the book of ephesians
chapter five again that's ephesians
chapter five
you know one of the things we learn
about jesus and his sacrifice for us
is merits what he did for us when you
look at the book of ephesians chapter 5
we read right there in verse 2
ephesians 5 and verse 2 it says and walk
in love
as christ also hath loved us and hath
given himself for
us an offering and a sacrifice to god
for a sweet
smelling savor christ is that sweet
incense his
merits constitutes that sweet incense
but then in addition to that
we have a real beautiful privilege we
have a privilege
to do something that can mingle with the
incense of christ's merits his work that
he did on our behalf
his sacrifice what are those things that
we can do that also is representative of
this
incense it's in revelation chapter 5.
in revelation chapter 5 we discover
something else about the incense
it says in revelation 5 and verse 8
and when he had taken the book the four
beasts and four and 20 elders fell down
before the lamb
having every one of them harps and
golden vials
full of odors that word otis and the
greek is incense
which are the prayers of the saints
now i want you to watch this this is
sweet man sometimes people say
you know i don't know if you ever had
somebody do this before where they say
hey i don't feel up to praying can you
can you have somebody else pray for me
because i don't feel like god hears my
prayers but maybe he'll hear somebody
else's prayer
i remember back in the days when i was
part of a church and i would hear this
sister pray
and the sister could pray like fluent i
mean she would just
flow not stumbling over her words or
anything
and a lot of us said man surely the lord
must hear her prayers i mean she prays
so beautifully so eloquently and all
these other things
and we begin to think that people's
oratory skills
or their beautiful way that they put
words together
somehow impresses god which is crazy
because god is like look i'm the creator
of words you can't impress me with words
and so god is not looking for you and
how to come to him with some flowery
words
what he wants us to come to him is in
sincerity of heart and
in agreement with his word and so when
we pray
i'm going to show you how you can have
assurance that god can hear your prayer
it's in revelation 8 in revelation 8 we
find the combo
of what we just studied again the
incense represents christ's
merits but the incense also represents
the prayers of god's people
now watch how in revelation eight they
both come together
in revelation the eighth chapter in
verse three i love it
it says and another angel came and stood
at the altar having a golden censer
and there was given unto him much
incense
that he should offer it what's the next
word
after it with the prayers
of all saints upon the golden altar
which was before the throne
notice the prayers of the saints is not
in and of itself the incense
the prayers of the saints have the
privilege of being
mingled with the incense it says it
again in verse four
it says and the smoke of the incense
which came
with the prayers of the saints ascended
up before god
out of the angels hands when you and i
pray in the name of jesus when we pray
lord i know i'm not worthy but i know
that your father finds everything about
you acceptable
when we pray in the name of christ and
ask upon his blessings confessing and
acknowledging our weaknesses and our
sins
but trusting in his merits that we might
be accepted in the beloved
every single prayer prayed in that
understanding
is acceptable with god and that is so
important that we learn through the
sanctuary
and so in the holy place we have jesus
our priest that intercedes for
us and that shoe bread and that light
and that
incense is showing us things about
christ
and also about us in our walk with him
but eventually the time comes at least
once a year that we gotta move
and we move from the holy and we enter
into the most holy so pastor myers
help us understand the most holy because
we're getting a lot closer to azazel
and we're gonna get ready to understand
some things about the scapegoat and how
god separates us from our sins it's very
exciting so go ahead and take us to
the most holy place